all right hello this is active inference
model stream
11.1 we're with Hadi vafa we'll be
discussing the recent paper puton
variational Auto encoder there'll be a
presentation and a discussion so thank
you to
you all right thanks for having me um
all right I'm excited to tell you about
this new work that we did um along with
Jake who's my postart mentor and deel
who's a PhD student in our
lab so the big picture motivation behind
this work is that we think we're going
to understand the brain through this
study of brain-like artificial neural
networks but why do we think this way so
all right think about a dream experiment
where we recorded every single neuron in
the brain of many animals doing
complicated tasks in their natural
environments we also have um electron
microscopy connectome of every single
neuron and then you know learning
Dynamics is available to us as well we
know everything about that those
brains um this experiment is very
difficult it's probably going to be
impossible for the next I don't know 50
million years but if we had that data
the challenges we don't even know what
to do with that kind of data set so the
idea is that we're going to going to use
a&n as computational models of the brain
to generate knowledge and uh theories
and computational uh models to be able
to analyze that kind of data whenever
they're available so that's that's the
motivation but there's a challenge here
so if you want to use Anns to study the
brain you better make them brain likee
because you know as the cliche saying
goes um all models are wrong but some
are useful and uh the degree of
usefulness of these Ann is um is it
corresponds to how brain-like they are
and in in this particular work I'm going
to show you uh what I mean by brain like
it it's it this word could mean many
different things to different people but
I have a very specific meaning in mind
which I will tell you about and in in
this work our focuses on models of
visual perception so we're going to
build Ann model uh that perceives visual
stimuli and we're going to make it brain
likee that's the whole
idea so if you want to build um brain
like models you better draw inspiration
from neuroscience and the idea is that
we want to narrow down our search space
because the the space of alln is
huge and these are the specific there
there are three Inspirations that we're
going to rely on perception is inference
rate coding and predictive coding I'm
going to describe each of these U
separately
first let's start by
this all right so there's this idea that
perception um involves two components
there is this external component that is
provided to us by the sensory data U for
example the photons that land on your
retina and there's this internal
component you have some subjective
experience by living this world that
gives rise to Prior expectations that is
combined with the sensory data to give
rise to perceptions
and this idea is not really new um you
can trace it back to over a thousand
years ago uh by Al Housen he mentioned
um Vision occurs in the brain rather
than the eyes and he was the first to
discuss the subjective U elements of
perception and also more famously
helmholdt said perception is our best
guess as to what is in the world given
our current sensory evidence and our
prior experience and the current sensory
evidence is just this external component
and prior experience is the internal
component let me give you an example
so this is known as the ases room
illusion we see this image and we
immediately think that oh this must be a
giant man and this must be a really
short man but in reality um there's a
bit you know different explanation so U
this room is designed in a very specific
way to give rise to this illusion so we
usually think rooms are rectangular like
this dashed line over here but this room
is not and um the sensory data that is
coming from person a on this corner is
consistent with two different uh
possible explanations one explanation
that the room is rectangular and uh the
person is short and the other
explanation that the actual explanation
is that the room is not rectangular that
the person's standing far behind person
a and that's why we we see it as short
but you know because we have this PRI
expectation built in in our brain by by
you know living in this world where uh
every room or most rooms we encounter
are rectangular we immediately just
default to this explanation that oh yeah
this person must be short so that's the
idea we are prior expectations can
actually trick us into perceiving things
that are not true
and you can actually formalize this
using mathematics of beian um
probability
so here I'm going to introduce you very
briefly to the idea of a generative
model imagine you have some latent
variable Z that you can sample from from
the prior P of Z and then condition some
likelihood function based on whatever
you sampled and then sample some
observation X so so X could be an image
Z could be some abstract latent
variable now within this context it's
interesting to ask if I saw some
observation um some image x what are the
likely causes underlying generation of X
and that's the reverse Direction so we
have inference where we want to um
compute this beian posterior P of Z
given X which according to Bas rule is
proportional to these terms and I'll
explain what they are so inference goes
in the reverse direction from the image
to the underlying cause of that
image and now let's actually relate this
back to that quote earlier from
helmholtz so he says perceptions our
best guess that's the posterior U over
here as to what is in the world given
our current sensory evidence that's the
likelihood function and and our prior
experience and that's the blue over here
so um we think um or the theory of
perception as inference states that
that's really what's going on in the
brain when you show an image to the
brain um the brain thinks what latent
configuration likely caused my current
observation and in order to answer that
uh we need to compute a posterior
distribution over some latent causes
given than the observation this is the
essence of perception as
inference next thing is rate coding and
this idea is okay how do biological
neurons communicate and store
information we know that neurons produce
all or non Action potentials or we call
them
Spike and um the first evidence that
neurons use U so so rate coding is the
idea that uh neurons in code information
in the rate of these
spikes and this comes this goes back to
all the way to 1920s where Adrian and
zman build amplifiers to be able to
measure spikes and they show that um if
you apply some stimulus to some neurons
their firing rate increases and um in a
in a proportional way to the magnitude
of that stimulus and and this type of
figure you can see it in any uh in many
other different Neuroscience papers um
you know here they have some weight that
is hanging from the muscle but you can
actually you know um this this situation
happens when you show a stimulus and
record from visual neurons or play a
sound and record from auditory neurons
and so on so the idea is that there's a
baseline firing rate or number of spikes
per second and then whenever some
stimulus is shown to the brain the
firing rate increases uh which encodes
or represents the presence of that
stimulus this is the idea of rate coding
we're going to put this in our
model last uh the idea of predictive
coding um the summar is that brains can
be thought of as predicting predict uh
prediction machines this is the first
sentence that this uh beautiful review
by Andy Clark starts the the abstract
starts by saying uh this BAS
basically and you know the summary of
the idea is that the brain contains an
internal model of the
environment the brain uses this internal
model to predict or anticipate sensory
inputs and then when the sensory inputs
actually um re you know are received by
the brain uh they're compared to the
predictions and then there are some
errors of course because even though we
live in a predictable World um it's not
fully predictable there's always some
things that the brain is going to miss
and those are the errors and these
errors are propagated up the cortical
hierarchy to update and um maintain this
internal
model and and you know this predictive
coding idea uh and perception as
inference they have some um they're
overlapping Concepts but um but
ultimately they're distinct and we're
going to put all of these in our models
here are some references if you are
interested if you combine these three
ideas it Narrows down your searches
space to this model which we call paan
variational Auto encoder the paan part
comes from rate coding U because in
computational Neuroscience there's a
long history of modeling uh The observed
Spike Counts from real biological
neurons using a poson distribution
conditioned on some rate variable the
variation Auto encoder part comes from
perception as inference because if you
actually formulate um you know what hel
said in in modern basian terms it turns
out that these these architectures
variational Odo encoders exactly
optimize for that uh loss so um that's
why they're they're very very similar
and then along the line down the line
I'll I'll show you how predictive coding
is you know Incorporated in this
model okay but before um telling you
about poon variational Auto incoder I
should tell you what is a vae or Auto
auto encoder so the architecture um has
two components in the simplest vaes
there's some input it could be an image
and it gets encoded by this encoder
Network or you can refer to it as
inference recognition these are U you
can use these interchangeably to you
know infer some latence or infer some
posterior distribution conditioned on X
and then you can samp from that
posterior and
decode map this latent back to the
observation and the idea is that when
you are encoding this image into some
set of latent z um this encoding process
should be good enough that the latent
should contain enough information about
the input image such that you can
actually reconstruct it back that's the
idea and that's the um what word
autoencoder means because you're mapping
some input to
itself and you know can have different
forms um uh but but the last function is
um you want
to you want to actually just do
posterior inference and this is um what
the posterior is p of Z given X
proportional to
this and what we want to do is
approximate this true but intractable
posterior with
some Q which we are going to refer to
this as approximate
posterior and we're going to
parameterize it with some Theta and
learn those parameters such that this
term here is minimized this is the K
Divergence of Q and P um you can think
of it if q q is identical to P this term
is going to be zero but if Q is
different from P it's going to be non
zero a positive value
and actually if you just do some math
and arrange some some terms you end up
with this loss I'm not going to derive
this because this is pretty standard you
can look up um you know any tutorial or
blog post on vaes and they're going to
explain this but what we end up with is
this term called evidence lower bound or
elbow which has two components so the
first component is this expectation over
q log of P of x given Z and if you think
about this is like it Maps some Laten to
observations and we want to maximize
this term so we going to refer to this
first term as the Reconstruction term
because um it will have a high value if
your reconstruction is is is good and
there's this other term now another K
term emerges but this time between the
approximate posterior P of Z given X and
the prior which is different than this
and and this we're going to just refer
to this as
kter and it's called evidence lower
bound because this relationship holds
elbow is always less than or equal log
probability this is called Model
evidence that's why it's evidence lower
bound it's it's it's a lower bound on
model evidence and if you actually
multiply elbow by minus one it turns out
that this is exactly the variational
free energy which is larger than
surprisal which is negative log p and
this variational free energy is exactly
the same thing as as it appears in
Frisian free energy
principle so okay VI elas we're going to
maximize elbow or equivalently minimize
variation of free
energy now let's talk about um how do
you actually let's get a little more
specific so we're going to build a gaing
VA um I I should have mentioned that you
know the the choice of probability
distributions all the prior posterior
likelihood that's up to the practitioner
you have you know um you have freedom to
choose any distribution you want but you
know most of the literature in vaes is
actually just using gaussians for those
distributions our contribution is we're
going to replace gaussian with with pan
but let's actually just understand what
gaussian bees are about
okay so both uh prior and posteriors are
gaussians the prior is chosen to be a
fixed standard gaussian with zero mean
and unit
variance and uh this is again another
choice you can actually learn the prior
but in standard vaes there's no
learnable learnable parameter it's just
a fixed distribution and the posterior
is parameterized with some mean and
variance that is produced by the encoder
Network
and if you just compute the K term um
this is what you get again I'm not going
to derive this because pretty standard
at this point and and from this close
form solution to the kale term you can
see that it will be zero then mu is zero
and sigma is one that means the
posterior collapses the prior this is
known as as posterior collapse so if
they're identical of course they're
diver is going to be minimized which is
equal to
zero and um operationally this is what
happens when you have a gaan be so you
give it an present an image to the
encoder and it spits out some mean and
variance vectors and um it's red that
means it's parameterized by the encoder
Network and so on and then you construct
this posterior distribution this is the
same as Q of Z given X and then you
sample some latent from it this
distribution and then you map this
sampled latent back to its
reconstruction and this this is what
happens during the forward pass but you
want to be able to compute U the loss
you know you you want to take this x hat
and and compare it to X and you know
compute gradients update your parameters
but it's impossible to do it um if if
you actually just um sample from this
posterior
um and to to you know um circumvent this
problem the original vae paper
introduced the reparameterization trick
so instead of sampling from this
distribution which is your posterior you
can sample noise from some you know unit
Gan and then compute Z as Mu plus
Epsilon times Sigma it turns out that
sampling from this distribution and and
this operation they're exactly identical
but but this is better because now you
can actually compute gradients and use
back propagation to learn uh your
Network's
parameters so what we're going to do is
we're going to replace these gaussin
with pan because of the rate coding idea
that's the
inspiration um and in order to make this
vae work we need to do two things first
of all we need to introduce an
equivalent reparametrization trick uh
for the poan case we also need to
compute the K term we're going to do
both of those in the next few
slides all right so as I mentioned now
we just take the prior and and posterior
we're going to replace gaussin with with
pan and so gaussians need both mean and
variance you have to Define both a mean
and a variance to have a gaussian
distribution but for pan you only need
one number that's just the rate
parameter and and this is the PDF of a
pulan distribution give me a rate and I
have this distribution so we have this
prior rate and the posterior rate which
depends on
X and and this could be you know any
general you can you can learn the prior
rates you can you know output any some
some generic posterior rate but here is
where we add the predictive coding
assumption we say that okay look let's
call the prior rates just R and
interpret those as some representation
units that are just maintaining a
prediction or anticipation of what is
coming what kind of sensory information
is is coming their way and then let's
assume that the posterior rates are
actually just um the a modulation of
those
existing rates so we just say take R and
the encoder only computes some quantity
we call it delt r that is a function of
the specific stimulus shown to the
encoder and then you you obtain the
posterior rates by multiplying these uh
two
together and and this is just an
illustration of the idea so you have
this input it is processed by some
encoder to produce Delta R and it is
understood that this Delta R is going to
interact multiplicatively with existing
prior rates and then once you have this
you know multiplication you're going to
now you have your posterior distribution
this is your approximate posterior and
then once you sample from this um you're
going to get discrete P counts because
now you have Plus on in the gaussian
case you would get continuous values but
now we're going to get discrete integers
which is Illustrated over here like for
example let's say we have five neurons
in the latent space we sample from this
posterior we have a vector of 1 3 0 0
one so we take that Vector we pass it
through the encoder and the encoder
learns to map it back to whatever image
that was
shown and um these are all learnable
parameters so the decoder Network the
encoder Network and the prior rates
they're all learnable
parameters so I want to emphasize
there's like a bunch of difference um
between pulan and gaussian bees the
first difference is okay it's pulan it's
not gaussian the other difference is
prior is
learned and and then the last difference
is that the these prior rates are
parameters that are shared between both
the prior and the approximate
posterior now let's talk about the POS
onization trick we want to be able to uh
when we sample event counts or Spike
Counts from this Plus on distribution we
want to be able to um differentiate
through this operation a so how can we
do
that in order to show you the um the
intuition behind our rization trick
let's actually focus on the process that
generates event counts so if if Z is
some event count that is distributed
according to
Pon we know that um there are some inter
event intervals that are distributed
through according to this exponential
distribution what delta T is is that
suppose one event has
happened um how how long do you have to
wait until you observe another event
those weight times intervent intervals
they're distributed according to this
exponential distribution with parameter
Lambda and and this is just a well-known
property of Plus on distribution we're
going to use this we're going to exploit
this fact to you know introduce our our
trick
all right so now suppose we want to
actually just run this process um sample
many times from this exponential
distribution and then um in a finite
window of observation time of 1 second
we want to see how many events would we
get so when we sample from this
exponential maybe we get first uh time
weight time is Delta T1 so we wait this
much until we observe the first event we
sample again it takes this much time to
observe the second event again third
event but the fourth event doesn't
really occur between zero and one which
is our previously defined observation
time therefore this doesn't count so we
have a total of three events because the
sum of these uh three Delta T's is less
than one so um sampling these from
exponential and and then counting them
like that like I like we did is
equivalent just sampling from posant and
getting like number three as our Spike
count so we can actually just sample
these numbers in parallel from the
exponential distribution we compute
their cumulative
sum uh which is visualized over here and
you can just apply the thresholds and
say all right whatever number of
cumulative sums that there's less than
one let's take that as our um Spike
count and here which means we're going
to have three events and and this is not
going to count and any other delt T's
after this is not going to count because
it's just going to add over here it's
it's it's extends beyond our weight time
so again we have total event counts of
three it turns out that you can just
take this and turn it into an
algorithm um so the input to the
algorithm is just some rates that are
produced by the encoder Network then we
have uh we have to specify how how many
exponentials samples that we want to
generate there's a temperature that that
controls the sharpness of the
thresholding so if you want to threshold
put a hard threshold of like anything
less than one uh that's not going to
work you have to um approximate that
with some sigmoid uh that's what we have
over
here okay so that's our reper
metrization trick and um and we hope
that this this trick you know it can you
know be used beyond the realm of vaes
for example in spiking real networks uh
people deal with this issue all the time
you know it's it's really difficult to
work with discrete stochastic variables
so we're hoping that this algorithm will
find applications elsewhere as
well but now let's talk about um the
loss function derivation as a reminder
we have our prior given like this and
the posterior given like this and our
goal is to compute the K
ter so let's first start by just
definition of the KL term um for any
distribution q and P the KL between q
and P is um this expectation over Q of
log of Q / P so so far this is just
general definition but now we're going
to plug in the actual poson
distributions that we
have so just put that over here we
Define Lambda to be R * Delta R it's
just our posterior rate and this is what
Plus on distribution looks like so I
just replace q and P and immediately we
see that Z factorials cancel and we can
actually just um write this term as
follows it's just log of Lambda over R
to the^ Z
Plus log of e to the minus Lambda plus
r and then Z comes down Lambda over R is
Delta R so you're going to just end up
with Z log Delta r and log of e to
something is is very simple it's just
you know you bring the exponent down and
in this entire expression the only thing
that that has an expectation is z
everything else is a constant so it
comes out and the expectation of z uh
over Q is just it's the mean and the
mean of poson distribution is just the
rate so Z is going to be replaced by
Lambda which is the rate of Q and that's
we get here so R minus Lambda plus
Lambda log Delta
R and again we just take R take it out
and it's like 1 minus Delta R plus Delta
R log Delta R so we see that nicely um
by having you know by virtue of choosing
this kind of predictive coding like
assumptions our K term nicely factorizes
to a term that depends on prior and
another term that depends on the
modulation that comes from the encoder
and then we Define this whole thing in
parentheses to be F so that's f is 1
minus this plus whatever and if you plot
it it looks like this so Delta R is by
definition always positive it's greater
than zero and um if Delta R is one it
says like okay do not modulate anything
let's just keep the prior rate then this
F becomes zero and if Delta R is really
large you you pay the cost of you know
it it increases the magnitude of f of
Y so okay so this scale term was just
for one neuron um if you have K
statistically independent neurons K
being the dimensionality of our latent
space you can just easily extend this
derivation to see that the KL term is
just the sum of of these
terms and now this is the interesting
part we're going to interpret this term
as a metabolic cost term
the reason is are you know the the prior
firing rates they are positive values by
definition and we ended up with some
term F that also is positive by
definition so you have a positive term
multiplied by another positive term so
this thing whole thing is is just a
positive value and we want to minimize
it and we can minimize this for example
by just putting zeros in all of our
prior rates like all of these these
neurons are silent they're not doing
anything and and that's why um we are
interpreting this as a metabolic cost
because you know producing Action
potentials um is is a very costly
metabolically costly operation so the
neurons in the brain they don't want to
fire Action potentials unless it's
absolutely necessary to encode some
information or communicate something
that's why U this is very
interesting that it just comes out of
the math
and if you just put everything together
this is just the the loss of Plus on vae
the first term is the Reconstruction
term um it's just the L2 Norm of X
input minus reconstruction this is like
decoder Network applied to one sample
which is drawn from the posterior uh so
this is the Reconstruction plus this
term which is comes from the KL term and
this is very curious because now we have
some some term that says like
reconstruct the image and another term
that says do it while uh optimizing or
or minimizing neural resource use and
this is reminiscent of sparse
coding which I will introduce here so in
96 um old s and field introduced sparse
coding they said okay let's imagine
there are some images X and some latent
variable z um or like let's say neural
activation z in their case um and let's
assume that we represent these images as
a linear sum of some basis elements from
a dictionary
fi while we're representing these images
let's also try to minimize the magnitude
of neural activity which is this L1 term
over here and just um you know minimize
this whole loss
that'll give you sparse coding spse
because you know if you if you apply
this term it's going to push a lot of
these uh neural activities to zero it's
going to give you a sparse activity
vector and and this really
resembles what we get from
pvee and in order to actually make this
connection more clear we just take this
General decoder term that appears in the
loss we also assume we have a linear
decoder just like sparse coding and it
turns out in that case you have a closed
form solution for the law um I'm not
going to derive this it's in the paper
if you're curious but you know there is
a close form solution um in in the
actual you know full loss there is this
expectation value which you can compute
it gives you this final
loss and again we see this this
correspondence nicely so there is one
term that says um Faithfully represent
images with some linear
decoder um and then there are two terms
here actually it's as opposed to just
one there are two terms that push your
firing rates to low values so this
diagonal of Pi transpose Pi is positive
by definition and Lambda is positive so
this thing needs to minimize therefore
it forces Lambda to minimize and again
just a reminder that this is coming from
the K term and we interpret it as a
metabolic cost ter okay so let's just
pause a little bit here he started from
all those um three Neuroscience
Inspirations we said we want to build a
model that does um you know perceives
visual inputs we want to build
in um perception as inference rate
coding and predictive coding all of
those in the model it gives us it um it
gave us the the Bon vae idea we derived
the loss and we saw that uh it resembles
spse coding so it's just U gifted To Us
by the theory now we want to test this
we want to say okay the loss resembles
sparse coding but let's actually just
train some models and see if we get
sparse coding like results that's what
we're going to do next
experiments oh yeah this is okay so this
is the architecture of um linear PVE so
you have again some image is encoded
into delt R multiplied by R to give you
this posterior and importantly now the
decoder is just a linear layer that's
what this is about and another uh
important assumption that um is Central
to sparse coding is that you have to
have an over complete latent space so
you have many more latent Dimensions or
many more neurons than you have pixels
so m is the number of pixels of the
input image K is your latent
dimensionality now we're going to train
this model and compare it to sparse
coding but also um in order to
understand what component of the pvee
might you know um you know reproduce
Spar SC we're going to compare to
Alternative vae models so we have
discrete vaes we have pvee over here
which is what we introduced and we're
going to use um categorical vae uh and
there are continuous va gaussian va and
llas VA and the reason we chose llas to
to include in in this uh in this table
is that people have shown before us that
if you have a lloss distributed prior
you can also get sparse coding like
results so we want to test which one of
these models is actually uh more sparse
coding like if you
will and then we're going to compare to
actual you know um very well established
standard sparse coding algorithms one is
the locally competitive algorithm from
2008 it's a biologically inspired
algorithm that U uh optimizes the sparse
coding loss and another algorithm is uh
ISTA these are both very standard and uh
well established um as well as the
gaussians so you're going to compare to
a bunch of
models all right so if we train this
pvee
on linear pvea on natural image patches
this is what we get these are the
decoder
weights and um if you're not if you're
in Neuroscience in visual Neuroscience
you already know that these are we refer
to these are like the Bor patches and
and um these resemble the selectivity in
the primary visual cortex of monkeys and
and mice and and humans so so this is
very biology like and and for the first
time these types of Gabor patches they
they emerg from the sparse cating models
which we are we were able to reproduce
with
pvea and if I show you the other
models it's not actually trivial so
let's go from left so we have gaan VA
over here I'm not sure if you can see
but um there's a lot of noise and
there's only like last three rows uh
look you know they they they look like
PCA and and that's expected because a
linear gaing vae is theoretically
equivalent to probabilistic
PCA now we have also llas VA down here
um there are some Gabor that emerge from
the llas VA but again there's a lot of
dead neurons which I will Define what
dead neurons means and I I'm going to
show how we quantify them but you know
for now let's just visually inspect
these learned decoder rates this is the
posan vae and this is the categorical
vae categorical VA is discrete so it
also learns some Gabor but it's very
limited so um that there's a lot of
noisy elements and certain spatial
frequencies are missing and certain
orientations are missing as well from
the
category and finally in the last column
we have these results from the standard
sparse coding algorithms these are the
best you know uh game in town if you
want to learn sparse coding like U
dictionary
elements and we see that among the vae
models um posan V actually is the is the
like most similar one to these standard
sparse coding algorithms so in
conclusion because both U the loss
function of a PVE just emerged to
resemble sparse coding and also
empirically we you know tested it and
and also learns sparse coding like U
results we conclude that it actually
contains sparse coding as a special case
why because you know we we made a linear
decoder assumption so it's like PVE can
be um General like it could be anything
could be nonlinear encoder nonlinear
decoder but if you make the decoder
linear and make the Laten space over
complete you're going to recover bar
coding like
results okay so here's um how I quantify
number of dead neurons this is just a
let me just first Define what the
posterior collapse is this is a big kind
of prevalent issue in
vaes when a latent Dimension stops
encoding information it's going to be
always the posterior in that latent
Dimension is going to be identical to
the prior so there's no ation the K term
is very small or zero and that's how we
measure dead neurons and here this
dashed line shows the gap between the
post the kale of dead neurons and active
neurons that's how we Quantified and uh
we found that for the
pvee uh across three different data sets
it consistently had much larger number
of active neurons compared to l and
gaussian VA so it kind of automatically
avoids this posterior collapse issue
because of discreetness that's the the
main cause of this
observation okay so we want to actually
do some other experiments um so far we
just saw that if you start from those
Neuroscience Inspirations you get a
model that also you know recovers or or
reproduces some other Neuroscience like
uh models result like sparse coding but
now let's just um be a little more
General we want to evaluate PVE in a
general representation learning setting
that's what this is
about all right so we want to test these
UNS supervisor presentations on a
downstream classification task and we
use nness for that purpose we're going
to compare all those four vae models for
this task the approach is that after you
know the training is done extract
encoder representations this means we
push mest digits from the validation set
through the encoder we extract the
representations and we're going to do
things with those all right and then
once you have these representations
sample a limited number of supervised
labels so M this you know they have
labels we know each image of a digits
has a label so it's it's a supervised
data set um but we going to look at
subsamples like very small samples um of
of supervised um to sets and and the
reason is that you know um having labels
is expensive so if a model can achieve
good performance with a small subset of
supervised labels is is a is a good
model that's the
idea then we're going to apply kir
neighbor classifier um to to classify
these these um
digits and the idea of using KNN is that
it's a non-parametric model so you don't
need to learn anything on top of these
representations and the output of a K&N
classifier directly depends on the
geometry of representation so it's going
to tell us something about if there's
something fundamentally different about
the geometry of representations in one
of these vaes like PV versus the
others and then as you know as me
measure of success we're going to report
classification
accuracy this is the results um you know
we have different plat dimensionalities
we have different models there's a lot
of details that I'm going to skip but
let me highlight just one thing so let's
look at this number so for 10 latent
Dimensions with only 200 samples the
pvee achieves accuracy of around
82% but gaan vae requires five times
that number a thousand label samples to
achieve a similar performance in this
sense we claim that pvee is five times
more sample efficient than the standard
gaan vae and you know across the board
it just add performs all these other
models which shows that it learns useful
representations uh that can be applied
in Downstream
tasks finally let's let's quantify
sparsity uh we're going to use this
measure from V and Galant this is called
lifetime sparcity um zi is the response
to I stimulus
number of spikes in the
pan and N is the total number of
stimuli um just the intuition about this
formula is that um if if if if a neuron
only responds to a single stimulus and
doesn't respond to any other stimuli the
sparcity score is going to be one and if
the neuron or the latent Dimension
responds to all stimuli equally then the
sparity score is going to be zero so
zero means not sparse at all one means
uh very
sparse and we use that this is the the
y- axis the the lifetime sparity of of
these different um VA models and on the
x-axis we have the Reconstruction error
in mean squared
error um you see that posan is very
sparse but because of that sparcity it's
uh has larger reconstruction error
compared to let's say gaussian which is
down here and it turns out if you apply
some some Ru um to the gaussian it's
going to increase disparity but not as
much as Plus
on and then this curve over here came
from fitting a sigmoid to a bunch of Pon
vaes that were trained with different
beta so if you remember beta is a
parameter that um uh kind of changes the
trade-off between the Reconstruction
term and the KL turn so if you increase
beta you're going to get much sparer
results but uh at a cost of larger
reconstruction errors and if you if you
decrease the beta you're going to get
less sparse results but but better
reconstruction so that kind of traces uh
rate Distortion
tradeoff finally um one thing that we
Noti is that there is still a large
amortization gap for the pul
and I'll explain what that means so if
you compare pan with those standard uh
sparse coding algorithms including LCA
which is this dark grade and ISTA which
is this light grade we see that they
achieved the same level of sparcity
roughly uh but posang still has um a
larger reconstruction error but you know
what what happened here like what is why
is um LCA much better than pan VI so to
test this we we thought that you know
maybe the dictionary elements learned by
pan V are are are pretty good but the
actual inference is is not very good the
encoder architecture is not doing a good
job in inferring the activations so what
we did is we took the pan VA and we took
um sorry the the dictionary elements
learned by the Pang even applied LCA
inference on those and that gave us this
these
purple dots which we also fit a sigmoid
to and it turns out that you can
actually just close the amortization Gap
by applying a better inference which in
this case is the LCA inference to just
uh bring this over
here so the conclusion from this slide
is that the posan vae learns reasonable
dictionary elements but it's encoder or
the encoder architectures we tried in
this paper they weren't adequate and
there was this large geometrization gap
that in the future work we hope to to
kind of close this Gap by you know
building better encoders maybe iterative
encoders and so on okay let's just
conclude um so we started from these
three U Inspirations perception as
inference rate coding predicted coding
it gives us U this
architecture and um it's interesting for
many reasons because you know pan V
encodes its inputs in discrete Spike
counts therefore it's um more
biologically realistic and this
metabolic cost term emerged in the model
objective for free you didn't have to
put it by hand or anything and uh it
actually revealed this connection to
sparse coding which we verified
empirically and then from a theoretical
perspective uh it kind of Unites all
these different ideas like predictive
coding rate coding sparse
Under the Umbrella of beian inference
which is
nice and then the takeaway message is
that you know if you draw inspiration
from centuries of Neuroscience research
combine it with modern machine learning
you might get a model that's more brain
like than Alternatives so
um and it outperforms Alternatives in
key aspects like sample
efficiency all right this is all I had
for the slides um now if there are
questions could go over there or maybe I
can show the
code thank you that was awesome yeah how
about the code and meanwhile for people
who are watching write any questions and
then I'll ask them thank
you all right um yeah so I actually
haven't prepared anything specific to
say about the code but I'm just going to
riff through you know what what
exists um hopefully some some people
might find this inspiring okay so this
code is actually not online right now
it's not available but because the paper
is under review but uh once the paper
gets out um I'm going to make this code
publicly available so the maybe the more
more
important uh part of the code is that
you go in the code in the vae you have
va. py which has all the implementations
of different vaes that we discussed in
in this talk so there's a base vae that
um has all these different functions it
encodes um inputs you know you can have
a convolutional encoder you can have a
linear encoder MLP encoder it's all
implemented you know same with decoder
you have convolutional linear MLP it
computes the loss which is just the msse
um and you can also compute the exact
loss when you have a linear decoder
um so the KL loss is not implemented
because we're going to have specific
instances of vaes like L you know paulan
VA gin VA Etc and they each have their
own KW so that's that's not implemented
over here in the base vae and so on
there's there's a bunch of you know
different functions so let me just show
you the actual
implementations so posan V is over here
um
so in the forward Direction you have
this this infer function that accepts X
which is an image temperature and it it
computes so the self. log rate this is
the prior rates these are parameters
that are learned along with every other
parameter and you have this log R um
then you have log Dr Dr is just a delt R
that's the output of the encoder where
you encode the image as an output you
get log Dr
and then um skip this part then you
compute you you make this distribution
and and just to remind yourself that
this is just Plus on which I will show
you later it's defined somewhere else
and then you you make this distribution
you provide the log rates this is the NX
if you remember from the
reparameterization um slide you have to
provide how many exponential samples
you're going to draw
you know it's it's adaptively computed
somewhere else in the code I'll tell you
where later you provide the temperature
and then you have a
distribution which you know this is
going to be the infer function provides
you with the distribution that's your
approximate posterior and then you
sample from it and get spikes you decode
those spikes that's your reconstruction
that's
it there's other functions that I'm not
going to go but maybe like let's have a
look at the K term so um you can easily
you know understand this you know if you
understood the the slide deriving the
kale term in theory then you would
understand this
term um maybe I'll I'll show you quickly
the
distributions
so we have also
this
based
distributions which contains our
implementation of the pon distribution
and the
reparameterization trick for
it
um there we go it's here yeah so you
provide it with log rates um in
initialization you provide the
temperature which is the thresholding
temperature number of exper number of U
exponential samples and the clamp is
just basically says if the rate is
larger than e to the this you know it
applies a soft clamp which is e to the
this value so it applies an upper bound
on the rates this is for the you know
stability of training it's like U not
very
important but the important part is here
this function that's our
reparametrization algorithm okay so
first of all you initialize this
exponential distribution in this init
function so you you get log rates apply
the soft clamp and then you define rates
as this just uh exponentiate log rates
plus this really tiny value so that it's
non
zero um because if it's zero then this
exponential is going to raise an error
it has to be uh slightly above zero so
you define this exponential
distribution which takes the rate as
input and here I'm just borrowing from P
torch so this uh if I go
up I'm importing oh it's not over here I
imported somewhere else but
basically um where is
it this is the torch. distributions I'm
I'm just importing it as thiss so this
exponential is exactly pytorch's
implementation all right once we've
initialized this self. X object then you
can actually just perform pre
parameterized sampling so X is just the
first you know all those Delta T's that
I showed in the slide these are your x's
and you have your sample n times and
then you perform this cumulative sum to
get the times and
then if temperature is greater than zero
you have this soft indicator which is
just sigmoid you know if it was
temperature was Zero then you would have
have this hard indicator which is just
times less than one if if you take this
operation if you make it continuous you
will get this basically that's the
idea once you have this indicator
function then you can sum them in the
First Dimension to get your Spike
counts all right so that's that's for
the PA on but I want to also
mention this um continuous VA because
this is a more General implementation
that you can use for any you know any
vae that uses a continuous distribution
like in our case we used gaussian and
llas but you can actually take this
implementation and Implement easily
build your own continuous VA like Ci or
any other distribution you like as long
as you can you can reparameterize it
which a lot of pytorch you know
implementations they have this function
called R sample which is per
sample but again there you know this is
a very Sim similar idea you encode some
features take some X encode it into this
feature H and then because for these
continuous VES you need both the mean
which is location and the variance which
is log scale so you just divide H into
two parts you get these parameters and
then you you know construct this
posterior distribution and
then return it that's what infer does it
always G gives you the posterior
distribution once you have the posterior
distribution you can R sample or
reparameterized sample to get your
latence U ignore this part you know if
you can actually just apply an
activation function this is the gaussian
pr Ru that I I kind of skipped that
didn't really talk about it but that's
that's there and then you can decode and
Y as your reconstruct
so so this this continuous VA
implementation is is fairly complete you
can in order to build your own that's
all you have to do so just say Okay I
want to make a gaussian VA I'm gon to
inherit continuous VA object I'm going
to say okay self that this should be
normal that's it and for llas again you
inherit the continuous V and just say
the distribution should be L plus and
you can do this for any other continuous
uh distribution maybe um that you know
these are these are py Tores
implementation so any continuous
distribution implemented by pytorch that
has reparameterized sampling um you can
you can use this to build your own vae
and then we have this
categorical um which I'm going to skip
but you know we use the again P torches
implementation and okay so so this this
um this module defines vaes and um
there's another module that trains them
so let me just briefly go over
that again there's a bunch of code that
just defines base trainers there's a lot
of details here that maybe not very
interesting but you have this trainer
that accepts all these different vae
types poson gaussian categorical
loss and it goes through this is just
one
iteration um there's a validation
function all of that and it's it's
fairly complete so there's a bunch of um
arguments that you have to provide to be
able to run this code but because I
spent a lot of time to make it intuitive
it's going to be just a single line if
you want to train your own
PVE um you can just run uh that with a
single line like you know train vae you
specify the architecture in one string
you specify the data set and um and the
GPU that you want to train on and then
then you can actually do that if you
want but yeah this this code is not
available right now when I put it online
I'm going to make some
documentation and you know put some
scripts that make make it easy and
intuitive to just train your own model
if you're
interested there's a lot more but I
think at this point I'm going to stop
yeah there's there's a bunch of other
stuff um that is secondary
yeah
awesome okay while I um crop back the
screen maybe just let's start with how
did you get to this problem were you
pursuing Pon distributions and this came
up or how did you kind of um in your
research path come to this
approach oh so the the real initial
motivation is just you know
um we we did another paper um last year
on a gaussian vae that was hierarchical
and we found that that was um we trained
that gaussian vae that gaussian
hierarchical VA on a motion data set and
we found that um it learned latent
representations that were very aligned
to real biological neurons from the
monkey brain so we have another data set
uh from
um the data set was they showed some
moving dots to monkeys and they recorded
from their Mt which is a brain region
that you know um that is responsible for
motion perception anyway we found that
these vaes actually have a really high
chance of being brain brain like and
that gave us motivation to to think
about okay how we can make them even
more brain like so Gan is just en code
inputs in continuous values that are not
you know um constrained by any any means
but we know that that's not how brain
works we know that neurons produce
spikes that's how they communicate so we
said like okay vaes have potential but
how how can we make them better that was
really the initial motivation
awesome well it just to kind of recap a
little bit of how I saw this often
parameters in biological or cognitive
modeling are modeled as continuously
dynamically varying because there are
certain simplifying assumptions however
the empirical data be it neural spiking
or events or like ants
foraging how do you bridge the discrete
events to The Continuous and
the um mathematical equivalence which is
well known between the event arrival
distribution with the Brant and the
waiting time I saw that as a way that
you implemented with the statistical
methods to and also in doing so
generalize like what was relevant for
the base model for continuous or
discreet and then how can that be
articulated with the statistical
packages so that there's
good course handles to explore
these learning
settings I think that's actually very
interesting and and and deep point you
know um even though neurons communicate
with spikes or discrete Action
potentials we when we are modeling them
you can actually think as um you know
the actual underlying Dynamics could
happen in a continuous space like for
example we had these log rates you know
those log rates are continuous values
between minus infinity and plus infinity
really I mean even though in reality it
doesn't go that far but they're defined
in if you have n neurons log rates are
defined in RN right and then uh you can
assume that the model is just doing some
trajectory like the brain is doing going
through some trajectory in that log rate
space and in each given time you can
actually take this that log rate and
then map it to some posterior by
computing the exponential of that to get
the rates and then draw samples and in
that sense you can actually see that a
continuous underlying dynamical system
can be mapped into a discrete
observation through through paon and
also that um every time point in the
Dynamics of the brain also corresponds
to some posterior inference so these
Concepts I think can be nicely you know
reconciled with this View
yeah that was great and to kind of
connect it to active inference and a
little bit of the precursors there with
SPM statistical parametric mapping the
whole setting is there's underlying
neural activity hidden State external
State and then there's noise plus signal
representing a static mapping between
the hidden and the observable what you
had as x and z so that's like the
partial observability sit situation and
then that's the experimental situation
but you don't get to observe neural
rates so like in the SPM textbook and
the kind of modeling you model it with
the Predator pre type models or with
dynamical attractors but you stay in the
purely dynamical and then that doesn't
let you get to the rate coding but also
people have integrated those models
however in more of a um two-step process
rather than the onestep UniFi
objective of the auto
encoder yeah so that's pretty
interesting so because rate is in a
sense the rate itself is a latent
variable right we we never observe it
the it's a it's a madeup concept really
by the theorists we say okay there if
there is an underlying rate and that is
producing these observed
spikes you know in the brain then then
you you can actually try to infer the
rate by observing many spikes over many
trials and so on so in that sense yeah
rate itself is a latent variable um but
that that maybe you shouldn't go there
because that like adds another layer of
complexity one question I had about rate
was if you're going to model it you kind
of can't get away from it as a
underlying dynamical variable because
there's going to be variability in delta
T variance amongst arrival time so maybe
it's an metronome but in the non-
metronome case there's going to be kind
of
like fast and slower intervals so that's
kind of the common filter question which
is or or ARA or any time series
ultimately how smoothly should you
interpolate that like with the
splines with what method will the data
kind of have a relationship with a curve
that has the smoother differential
properties that ultimately allowed the
close form solution and the simple
simple algorithms
mhm makes
sense um okay I'll see if anyone asks a
question but um just one question now
and then I'll ask maybe one or two more
um like where do you see this being
useful slash applied
now so we are actually currently
building um based on this observation
that there was a lot large amortization
gap between Clon vae and this uh kind of
relatively old sparse coding algorithm
from 2008 we one conclusion we drew from
that is that you know we need iterative
inference so right now the inference is
just one path you take one image you you
infer something Del to compute Delta R
and then you just get the posterior but
now suppose you have a sequence you have
a video rather than images and you want
to just keep iteratively making your
inference better and better such that
your um let's say your posterior at time
T informs your prior at time t plus one
that's like very essential to beian
thinking so we're kind of right now
developing that model and our hope you
know very long-term hope is that you
know when we add that component and
maybe we add hierarchical structure to
the latent space then we get like
something that is truly brain-like and
it reproduces what we've observed what
we've learned about visual processing in
the last like you know 50 years so if
you get that model then you can perform
in silico experiments in it learn
something about brain like visual
processing and so on so that's kind of
roughly
the the trajectory we
imagine
awesome is there anything else you want
to add otherwise I think this was
amazing on the theory and really seems
use use ful with the sample efficiency
all these other
features yeah um I guess that's it yeah
thanks for having me this was really fun
awesome
okay I'll just read one comment from
someone wrote great work thanks to ACM
and AG ha Hadi for sharing looking
forward to find out what a different
inference scheme could do to the results
and the effect it could have on the
metabolic cost
okay yeah thanks for the comment yeah
cool com that in mind all right thank
you see you all right thank you bye